[Music]
so we have been uh looking at uh dynamic
programming based methods for solving
problems so far solving mdps right so
why do we call them dyamic programming
method so what's the problem are we
solving here what is this a problem I
actually gave you the intuition in
assuming that you have a uh like
remember I talked about one step
problems right so I said that you can
assume that the value is uh uh one
step
uh problem where for the first step you
get the reward and then you have a cost
for termination or a value for
termination right I said you can think
of it as r + gamma * V so the GMA V is
the value for termination right so if
you think about what we did for Value
iteration said what I Ed I
get so was it fine did I introduce that
RSA
notation or did I write it as just
expected value
right right so we did this if you
remember
that so
suppose I'm in a specific state
right in which as soon as I take a
step the problem ends right the episode
ends right as soon as it take a step the
episode ends really I mean I'm not
asking you to hypothe it's really the
episode ends
okay if I do this
once on that if I say let start I start
off with a zero value
function right so this part will be zero
in fact this this really does not
uh play Ro but anyway this part will be
zero and then I'll just get the expected
reward right so I take I I start from
this state okay let's call it some S1 I
take one
step and I end okay some terminal State
I
reach and indic getor what let say plus
one or something
right so the vn+ one I compute will be
the value function for
S1 cor just one time I do this I'll get
the right value do you see what I'm
saying so that is a end point right if I
look at the state just before the end
point right in the very first iteration
I'll compute the right value for the
state
correct let's say I have another state
which is one step before
the
S1 right that's all that's the only
transition available from S2 okay so I
take there's an action I take S2 I from
S2 I take the action I'll go to S1 okay
so how many iteration should I run
before I get the value for
S2
two right so one way of thinking about
what this is doing is to say that this
computes a solution for end step
problem it computes the solution for an
endep problem and assuming that I start
from S Prime I'll end in end steps this
gives me the value right and this
confutes value for n + 1 right so that's
essentially where the the dynamic
programming aspect comes in so the
smaller problem the sub problem I solve
is the one for the endep prediction
right and then the larger problem I
solve is using this repeated
substructure so the value of a n plus
one prediction will be R plus the value
of nth prediction so this using this sub
problems and making it trying to solve
the larger problem makes it dynamic
programming stochastic dynamic
programming it's typically called
stochastic dynamic programming because
you mean all the stochasticity is there
right and it's really this works
respective of whether it is a finite
Horizon problem or not right so assuming
you stop in one step what is the
solution right here I'm saying you
actually get to the terminal state but
you can just think about forget about
terminal State any state can be a
terminal state but I I'll allow you to
act for only one time step I'll allow it
to act for two time steps three time
steps four time steps and I keep going
till I allow you to act for an infinite
number of time steps right uh so that's
essentially what uh value tion does so
it's it's like a dynamic programming
approach right that's why we say you
solve for n and then you use that sub
problem solution to solve for n+1 okay
so that's why it's called dyamic program
is that clear right so these classes of
methods both value iteration and policy
iteration so policy iteration also is a
dynamic programming method but it's a
little tricky to see what the uh dynamic
programming Dynamic program there is uh
but still it's also a dynamic
programming approach and so I'm going to
talk about a general class of dynamic
programming Solutions here but before
that I want to
introduce one other uh distinction
actually a couple more distin
distinction
so there something called asynchronous
dynamic
programming uh so if you think about
this is one step in the value iteration
iteration I mean so I'm assuming uh most
people
who have that in your notebook so I'm
not going to write out the entire value
iteration procedure right so that's one
step right that's one iteration in the
that's the main iteration in the value
iteration algorithm right so what is the
crucial thing to note here is that for
all
the VN +1
computation right I use VN on the right
hand
side right so one way of thinking about
it is okay I have this array right or I
have this data structure some array that
represents the value function at time n
so I use the array and compute the value
function at time n+ one so it's a
different
array right so I make I have n and then
I make another array which is n plus1
and I compute it and then I copy that n
plus one over to n and then keep doing
this right instead of that you could
think of a way of doing it where I do
this in
place I don't use two
arrays I don't use one array for n one
array for n plus one I can do it with a
single array so what that would mean is
when I suppose I have some ordering on
the stage I have to go through some loop
on the stage say for S equal 1 2 N or
something like that right so when I do s
equal to 1 right I'll be using the old
values
of VN so so I'll be using VN right when
I use S equal to 2 here I'll be using VN
for 2 3 4 5 to n but I'll use VN + 1 for
it so likewise when I use VN + one of
three when I'm Computing it I'll be
Computing VN + one
of two and one and VN of all the other
states okay now this is a little tricky
if you think about it
because it's no longer clear what I'm
doing right whether it's VN + 1 or VN +
2 suppose I come to State five okay and
all the transition from five is going to
State one and two so when I'm actually
Computing VN + one of five I'll be using
vn+ one of 1 and VN + one of two so is
it am I Computing VN plus one of 5 or am
I Computing VN plus 2 of
5 but I'm using the second iterate
of I'm using one further iterate of 1
and two
right
so in fact it's is not even clear
whether if you do it this way it'll
converge or not right it turns out it'll
converge right uh and it turns out that
I don't even have to do it in this kind
of uh you know sequential order right I
can do I can pick any
state right and then update its value
and then pick some other state right and
then update its value I can keep
randomly picking States and keep
updating their value using whatever is
the current stored value of its
neighbors right so instead of using that
right so I can do this I mean from from
an array point of view right so whenever
I update some value this will the right
hand side also will change so I just
keep picking States and I can do this
right so this is called asynchronous
mode for running dyamic programming so
the only condition I need now to make
sure this dynamic programming converges
is
is I have to S well apart from the other
things mean additional condition I have
to assume I have to ensure is that I
sample all the states at least at
least at least times
H number
huh at least once
once atast at least one at least
infinite number of times so that I can
ensure convergence okay I just waiting I
gave you a wrong que I waiting to see
what you guys will do right I I have to
apply the update in every state infinite
number of times for it to converge right
so that's the the convergence Criterion
we saw earlier right only as this the
itates tend to Infinity we have looked
at all the the fix Point theorems only
as the itates tend to Infinity do we
converge right so in that case uh so you
have to make sure that all the states
are sampled infinitely often right so
then it will converge so it doesn't
turns out it doesn't matter in what
order you sample them it's actually very
powerful result and it allows us to do a
whole bunch of interesting stuff right
in
fact it allows us to do uh something
called realtime dynamic
programming which is a very interesting
uh
algorithm which is almost like
reinforcement learning but not quite
there okay so one of the main problems
in uh doing uh value iteration and
policy iteration and things like that uh
is when you are working with really
large State spaces right when you're
working with really large State spaces
uh you'll be every time you do this
iteration right whether uh do it in a
synchronous or asynchronous fashion so
every time you do this
iteration right you basically run
through all the
states right so in fact if you think
about the amount of effort you spend in
Computing the solution you spend the
same effort in Computing the value
function for every
state right but that is not not often
needed if you think about any practical
problem there are many many states which
are very seldom
visited right so you want to spend more
effort in trying to discover the True
Value function for states that you visit
often right and states that you very
rarely visit you don't mind right so if
people remember
uh uh the the expected uh error
formulation that we used in machine
learning right so we always try to weigh
the error by the probability of actually
seeing the data
point so like that here I would like to
if I want to try to do an optimization I
would like to weigh the error with the
probability of me actually visiting that
state so now I I have some estimate some
we V hat of s right so when I'm
evaluating my performance I look at the
true V Star minus V hat right times the
probability of going to
S right you see that so why why do I
want to do
that
stes why don't
you doesn't matter Common Sense things
Common Sense things
yeah you want to spend comput power in
Computing some values you don't have
infinite computational power I mean we
just say nicely run run things till
Infinity you really don't have infinite
computational power so that's why we
gave you some Epsilon criteria so you
can be satisfi Epsilon optimal policies
and so on so forth right so you don't
have to run till Infinity but if I give
you a mdp which has
say 100 million
States
right so I don't even want to run it a
finite number of times on all the states
right there still a significant amount
of computation usually I have limited
amount of computation so now we have to
figure out how am I going to assign this
limited amount of computation and how am
I going to spend this limited amount of
computation so what you would really
like to do is spend a lot of time on
those states which you are likely to
visit under an optimal policy so you
don't want to miss out on states which
are good which which which you need to
execute an optimal policy right so one
way that people do it is the following
right they start
from they start from some State they
execute some
trajectory right then they look at
states that occur along those
trajectory right and do your dynamic
programming updates only on those
States then what you do is now you have
a value function right you have have you
have made some changes to the value
function and this implicitly gives you a
policy so we all know that right so you
know how to recover a policy given a
value function we looked at it we looked
at it from V we looked at it from Q
given a v function you know how to
recover a policy given a q function you
know how to recover a policy so now
recover a policy from this value
function right now run another
trajectory just by running this policy
so it's like a sample you're taking from
the world so it start from from the
starting State execute this policy see
which are the states that you
visit right and then run
your updates on those States but the
crucial thing to remember here is every
state you're running your dynamic
programming update like this you're
assuming that you know the your uh the
expected value of the reward you're
assuming you know your transition
probabilities and then with these you
are changing the value right so I'm not
worried about what was the sample I'm
getting here if you think of the Bandit
case whenever I draw a sample I get just
one reward right so in this case what we
are using the sampling
for just to determine which are the
states at which we have to do the update
right so not the reward and all that we
assume that the reward distribution
everything is given to us we only doing
the sampling to figure out which are the
states we have to do the updates in so
it's called real time dynamic
programming I mean the real time is
within codes here that's because you are
generating these trajectories uh using
the current policy so the the idea is
that as your policy as your value
function gets closer and closer to the
optimal value function uh the policies
become closer and closer to the optimal
policies and therefore the set of states
that you sample will be those that are
highly likely to appear under those
trajectories right for example if I have
to start here and go here right states
that are to the corners might not get
some pample that often you know I'll
probably start trying to go in a
straight line from here to here so we'll
start going like this after some time so
you can see that that will be some kind
of
a like an envelope of states that will
get sampled a lot right and I'll be
applying
the the the DP updates on those States
more than DP DPF on the other
things uh yeah sh this grid world when
I'm exploring once when I'm going from
the starting to the gold St how am I
exploding I mean once it's completed I
update the V vs of all those days how am
I next iteration how am I exploring I
need to explore some other part yeah
that's a good point so I I didn't talk
about exploration here so you never
behave greedily with respect to the
value function you always have some kind
of exploration you could do Epsilon grey
so we know about Epsilon grey right so
at every point so I look at the values
of the actions or values of the next
state and be greedy only with the
probability 1 minus Epsilon and then
with probability Epsilon I do something
random yeah you should do do
something right yeah so this is called
realtime dynamic programming it's
actually a pretty powerful method
provided you have your uh model
available to you this allows you to
focus your computation only on a small
number of states okay uh uh but but if
you want to ensure convergence in
realtime dynamic programming right uh
what is the condition you
need you have to visit every state
infinitely often I mean so it doesn't
matter that you fusing your computation
so what essentially dynamic programming
allows you to do is that given a finite
number of uh updates that you can do
okay it loves you to focus those finite
number of updates in things in states
which are more likely to be useful to
you right but uh given an infinite
amount of computation it will eventually
converge assuming that you have an
Epsilon set never going to
zero okay so con Cru IAL thing that you
should note here is in rtdp we use the
sampling only to figure out which states
to update okay nothing more than that
okay in if you move on when we actually
look at true reinforcement learning
algorithms you'll be using the sampling
to
determine not only the state stop date
right but also what is the reward that
you have to update it with because I
don't have this reward right and
also what is the the terminal cost
you'll use here what is the v v of S
Prime you'll use here because this also
I don't have this is the this is that's
why I said this takes you some ways
towards a full reinforcement learning
algorithm but it still a dynamic
programming solution because it uses all
the expectation in this okay good any
questions on
this
okay so how how many of you have been
reading ahead on this is what chapters
am I on in the book okay good so how
many of you have read chapter
4 you're my only hope man come on you're
disappointed me you're the only guy who
have been reading so far yeah uh anyway
uh yeah so I don't think rtdp is there
in chapter 4 right so so whatever I told
you is the thing if you want to read
more you probably have to pick up uh the
rtdp paper it actually is very well
written the original rtdp paper uh of
course I'm a big fan of Andy's writing
so I'll always say that but
uh yeah so the next thing I want to talk
about is a very very powerful technique
that we use called generalized policy
iteration so people remember policy
iteration right so it essentially has
two steps right so you
have policy evaluation right and then
you
have policy
Improvement
so what is asynchronous
DP just checking if people are listening
or
not you can yeah so you don't have to do
it in lock step right all the states
don't have to get updated in one one in
one iteration right so so there is no
actual definition of iteration itself is
gone here as synchronous DP okay anyway
so people know that's policy iteration
right so I have a policy evaluation step
right and then I have a policy
Improvement step the the pi stands for
policy Improvement not policy iteration
right policy evaluation policy
Improvement I keep doing this until my
policy doesn't change
anymore right and uh so we did do the
convergence of policy iteration I kind
of convinced you that policy iteration
would converge at least on finite mdps
so we have not done the convergence on
infinite State spaces I'm not going
going to do that because most of the
results I'll be showing you will be only
on finite uh State spaces mainly because
I need to develop a lot more mechanism
for showing you this on infinite State
spaces and it really belongs to a course
on on mdps not on RL right so it really
belongs to a course on mdp so if you're
interested I don't know so Rahul marate
used to teach a course in NS on mdps I
don't think he does that anymore so he
actually used to teach short of this so
whatever book I have been using to get
all this material for you it's called
uh um Marco processes by
putterman so what do we have uh copies
of the chapters from putterman or
something don't don't tell me if there
is an online version of putterman but
maybe you
should tell them not
me we don't have a version of
FO didn't I give one last year I think
you okay maybe you can pick it up from
the last year's material or something
exist whatever yeah but but don't try to
read it right so what I essentially did
was took three different chapters from
the book and Cherry pecked results that
I wanted to present here and then kind
of uh you know simplified the theorems
and other proofs and so on so forth and
presented it to you so if you actually
read Putman directly it in fact some of
you might be even confused as to where
the heck are those theorems he did in
class in the book right but I assure you
that that's a place to go if you want to
understand this better and that's where
I took this material from anyway so
going back to policy iteration right so
there is this technique
called generalized policy iteration
somewhat like asynchronous DP right in
the sense
that
it does the following so I have a policy
I have evaluated the policy right I
don't try to be greedy on all the states
in the value function I just pick some
states right and then I say okay I'm
going to change my policy by being
greedy only
here
right then I go back and do the
evaluation of this new policy
okay but then do I have to evaluate this
new policy in every
[Music]
state only which are updated uh not
really I have to evaluate it a little
bit more because states that are close
by which move in here their values will
also change because this value changed
so so I'll have to do some amount of
evaluation around the states where I
change it right in fact it turns out
that this works both ways so start off
with the
policy I don't evaluate it on every
state okay I evaluate it only on some
states just like we did in rtdp right
rtdp I did value
iteration right but instead of doing
value iteration right I could have taken
off this Max
here right I could have put a summation
over Pi so I start off with some
arbitrary PI right run this update only
on
trajectories right now I'll sample some
states I'll update the value function
there for the current Pi that I'm
following right and then what I do now I
go try to be greedy with respect to this
value
function okay now here it makes sense
only to be greedy with respect to those
States in which only to be greedy in
those States in which you change the
value function because other states it
wouldn't change because I'm only looking
at the value function and I try to be
greedy right so it not change uh but in
those states where I change the value
function I have to go go and do the GED
ification I'll change the policy now
okay now what I do I have a new policy I
can go back and sample some more States
according to this new policy and I do
the policy evaluation only on those
states that I sampled so I'm doing both
a partial policy evaluation and a
partial policy Improvement this is
called generalized policy
Improvement right so one way of thinking
about it is that instead of uh there's a
picture in the book which I don't like
so instead of uh doing a complete uh
evaluation or a complete Improvement
you're doing this partially with bits
and pieces right uh so uh why do you
want to do
this again we can save computation yeah
I have to remember the states you have
to remember the states in which you did
the policy evaluation and policy even
you don't really have to the most
effective you will get is if you do the
policy Improvement only on the states
where you evaluated the policy right but
you don't have to so I can always say
that I'll pick some random number of
states and then I'll go uh I'll pick
some random set of States I'll do my
policy evaluation there I'll go pick
another random set of states and do my
policy Improvement there if the
intersection is empty then you'll
probably not change my policy at all but
that should not be your shopping
criteria so you should have a different
shopping criteria when you're doing
generalized policy iteration right but
if your intersection is empty you
wouldn't stop and then I mean you
wouldn't change the policy now go back
and sample some more St so that way if
you do you'll be doing a lot of wasteful
computation right the all the policy
Improvement it did be wasted but you
don't need to remember random it's more
useful if you do it on trajectories so
why is
that I mean technically I mean rtdp
style of convergence right I mean if I
don't do it on trajectories it becomes
more or less like a synchronous DP right
but I'm claiming that rtdp will have a
greater effect than a synchronous DP
why those are parts that happen more
often I'm sorry not just happen more
often there's a slightly uh subtle Point
here when I'm looking along the
trajectory so I'm actually not only
sampling a state I'm also sampling a
successor I'm sampling a successor I'm
sampling a successor so there will be
changes you know when I when I'm trying
to update vn+ one
of remember I put put in some states
like
this S1
S2 s so now that I sampled S3 right I
will recompute the value of S3 that will
also affect the value of S2 right so now
because I'm sampling along the
trajectory I actually get the sequence
here so when I when I update S3 my S2
will also get updated my S1 will also
get updated so because of this
connectedness right so I'll actually
have a greater effect for that sample I
drew right if I had sample some S1
somewhere and S2 somewhere else and they
are not connected there's no way they
are going to I mean appear in each
other's update equations right then I'll
be using the same old values that I
had and I'll be trying to update
this so that's why so sampling along a
trajectory can be more effective that's
why you want to sample along
trajectories again you don't have to
right so what you're trying to do is so
you don't have to in the in the sense of
uh trying to uh uh show convergence
right all you need to do to show
convergence is you sample it infinitely
enough right so you don't have to show
that uh the samples are long
trajectories right uh it's possible that
if with a little no with a lot of work
you can show that your rate of
convergence improves if you're sampling
along trajectories uh but I'm not aware
of any such results that people have
actually worked out out
there maybe just because it's it's too
hard to show and it's not that much of
an interesting result anyway
uh but so people get the idea behind
generalized policy iteration
right in fact you can take generalized
policy iteration to an
extreme
how I can sample a
state okay take an one action according
to the
policy they have
right and then be greedy with respect to
the updated value
function so sample State take one
action right update the value of the
state now be greedy with respect to that
and produce a new policy only for that
state I'll change the
action right sounds too
extreme right so so this is policy
evaluation policy Improvement we talked
about right I just take some trajectory
I then do the policy evaluation on that
and then I do policy Improvement I keep
iterating this and I'm claiming it will
converge okay so I'm not going to show
you proofs of generalized policy
iteration converging but I'm claiming
that it will converge and trust me right
now the question I'm asking you is I'm
doing this only on one state at a time
pick a
state I pick an action according to the
policy right and then I update the value
function and then I change the policy
for the state to be greedy with respect
to that value
function I can do this by randomly
sampling States over the thing or I can
do this by sweeping through States I
start with S1 I'll do this I'll change
the policy there start with S2 do this
change the policy there and keep doing
this does it sound like a reasonable
thing to
do how can you be greedy when you huh
how can you be greedy when you take only
one
action why I just look at the value
function and then pick that one action
it gives me the maximum value right so
that's what I mean by
greedy I'm not saying that I have only
one choice to make choose from I'm
saying I have to take only one action I
have multiple choices among those I pick
the one that is greedy with respect to
the value
function we might getting a problem in
two steps if if there is a no we already
looked at an algorithm that does that
that's exactly what value iteration does
if you think about
it right so I pick the best
action right so I'm being greedy I pick
one step and then I find out what the
next next thing is and use that I update
the value function so next time I come
to the state I'll pick the best action
according to the the new iterate of the
value function right so this is
essentially what value does it's one way
of thinking about value iteration is is
an extreme form of generalized policy
iteration you pick a state pick a greedy
action right evaluate the policy then
change the policy right so in fact
you're rolling the policy evaluation and
the policy Improvement step has been
rolled into one equation
there kind of crazy
right so that's what valuation do think
of it generalized extreme form of
generalized policy right so if that
doesn't appeal to you don't worry about
it right but what we will do later is
that many of the reinforcement learning
algorithms that we will look at are some
form or the other of generalized policy
iteration okay so many many many cases
that we look at is some form or the
other of generalized policy iteration
and uh so one of the powers of power of
generalized policy itation is the
following so as soon as I come up with a
mechanism by which I can evaluate a
policy if I give you some policy I can
evaluate the policy that's all you know
right I can use that to turn it into a
mechanism for learning to solve the
mdp right if I give you a mechanism for
evaluating a policy I can turn that into
a mechanism for solving the mdp just
saying that I'm going to repeatedly
evaluate policies and then improve
between the evaluations right so as soon
as I Define a policy evaluation
scheme I can convert that into a uh
solution for the MTP itself so this is
essentially uh the framework that we'll
see in many of
the uh uh reinforcement learning
algorithms we'll look at right so we'll
first look at the the evaluation setup
right and then we'll look at the the the
optimal solution setup
[Music]
[Applause]
okay